<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Learning to SQI</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Learning to SQI</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:08:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://learningtosqi.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Overview</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 13:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/overview/</guid><description>SQISign is an isogeny-based signature scheme that exploits the Deuring correspondence, which connects the world of supersingular elliptic curves over $\mathbb{F}_{p^2}$ to the world of quaternion algebras. More precisely, we have a one-to-one map between the following objects:
Supersingular $j$-invariants over $\mathbb{F}_{p^2}$ (up to Galois conjugacy) $\leftrightarrow$ Maximal orders in $\mathcal{B}_{p, \infty}$ such that $\OO \cong \text{End}(E)$ (up to isomorphism). An isogeny $\varphi: E \rightarrow E_1$ of degree $D$ $\leftrightarrow$ an integral left $\OO$-ideal and right $\OO_1$-ideal $I_{\varphi}$ of norm $n(I_\phi) = D.</description></item><item><title>Working with Cyclic Ideals</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/cyclic-ideals/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/cyclic-ideals/</guid><description>In SQISign, we are most interested in a subset of integral ideals called cyclic ideals. This terminology is not standard, as they are usually called primitive, however we use this name in the context of SQISign to highlight their connection to cyclic isogenies (i.e., isogenies with cyclic kernel). They are defined as follows.
Definition. Let $I$ be an integral left $\OO$-ideal for some order $\OO$. We say that $I$ is cyclic if, for all prime $\ell$, we have that $I \nsubseteq \ell\OO$.</description></item><item><title>Correct up to Isomorphism</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/up-to-iso/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/up-to-iso/</guid><description>Informally speaking, the Deuring correspondence gives a bijection between maximal orders in the quaternion algebra $\BB$ and the ideals connecting them, to endomorphism rings of supersingular curves over $\mathbb{F}_{p^2}$ and the isogenies between them. However, when computing the isogeny from a given ideal under this correspondence, it will only be correct up to isomorphism. Conversely, the correspondence yields the correct ideal up to equivalence. In the context of isogeny-based cryptography, this does not pose a problem as we are only interested in curves up to isomorphism.</description></item><item><title>Pushforwards and Pullbacks</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/pushforwards/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/pushforwards/</guid><description>Throughout SQISign we are required to perform pushforwards and pullbacks of isogenies, and via the Deuring correspondence, an equivalent mapping for ideals. In this page, we discuss both of these maps, first from the natural perspective of isogenies and then show how we can perform the same mappings directly with the equivalent ideals.
Pushforwards of isogenies Say we have three elliptic curves $(E_0, E_1, E_2)$ connected by isogenies $\phi_1: E_0 \to E_1$ and $\phi_2 : E_0 \to E_2$ of coprime degree: $\deg(\phi_1) = N_1$, $\deg(\phi_2) = N_2$, $\gcd(N_1,N_2) = 1$.</description></item><item><title>Estimating Bounds for KLPT</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/klpt-bounds/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 00:08:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/klpt-bounds/</guid><description>The KLPT algorithm takes an input left-$\OO_0$ ideal $I$ and computes an equivalent ideal $J$ with norm dividing some smooth integer $\TT$. At a high level, this is accomplished with the following steps:
Compute an ideal $L \sim I$ with prime norm: $n(L) = N$. Compute $\gamma \in \BB$ with reduced norm: $\Nrd(\gamma) = L_1 N$ with $L_1 \mathrel{|} \TT $. Compute $\mu \in \BB$ such that $\gamma \cdot \mu \in L$.</description></item><item><title>Equivalent Prime Norm Ideals</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/prime-ideal/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 22:05:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/prime-ideal/</guid><description>The first step of the KLPT algorithm is to find an ideal $L$ equivalent to the input ideal $I$ with prime norm. The naive algorithm to compute equivalent ideals with prime norm is fairly simple, but getting SQISign to work in practice means being very careful with this step.
Practically, we want an ideal with prime norm, as we will need to perform computations modulo its norm. When it is prime, computations are easy and efficient.</description></item><item><title>Strong Approximation Lattice Trick</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/strong-approximation-lattice/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 09:02:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/strong-approximation-lattice/</guid><description>Overview The KLPT algorithm, which we call EquivalentSmoothIdealHeuristic(), takes as input a left $\OO_0$-ideal $I$ and a smooth integer $\TT$, and computes an equivalent ideal $J$ with norm $\TT$. There are four main steps:
Compute an ideal $L \sim I$ of norm $N$ using EquivalentPrimeIdealHeuristic(). Next, we run RepresentIntegerHeuristic() to obtain $\gamma \in \OO_0$ of norm $N\TT$. Solving the IdealModConstraint() on input $L, \gamma$ derives $(C_0 : D_0) \in \mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{Z}/N\mathbb{Z})$ such that $\mu_0 = j(C_0 + \omega D_0)$ where $\gamma\mu_0 \in L$.</description></item><item><title>Between Kernels and Ideals</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-kernel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 15:20:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-kernel/</guid><description>Central to constructive applications of the Deuring correspondence is efficiently converting between equivalent ideals and isogenies. The core of this work is converting between a cyclic ideal $I$ of norm $n(I) = D$ and a kernel generator $K$ of order $D$. This page is dedicated to discussing how to perform these conversions and follows the description of $\textsf{IdealToKernel}$ and $\textsf{KernelToIdeal}$, described by Algorithms 19 and 20 of Leroux&amp;rsquo;s Thesis.
Although we have attempted to make this page self-contained, we point an interested reader to both the first explicit formulation in [GPS17], and the clear and well motivated discussions from Leroux&amp;rsquo;s Thesis: Section 4.</description></item><item><title>Computing Isogenies from Ideals</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-to-isogeny/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 15:18:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-to-isogeny/</guid><description>Fundamental to SQISign is the Deuring correspondence. This gives us a link between the world of elliptic curves and the world of quaternion algebras over $\mathbb{Q}$. In particular, it tells us that the endomorphism ring of a supersingular elliptic curve $E$ defined over $\mathbb{F}_{p^2}$ is isomorphic to a maximal order in $\mathcal{B}_{p, \infty}$, the unique quaternion algebra ramified exactly at $p$ and $\infty$ (up to isomorphism). This correspondence extends to the maps between the elliptic curves: an isogeny $\phi: E \rightarrow E^\prime$ of degree $D$ between supersingular curves corresponds to a left integral $\mathcal{O}$-ideal $I$ of norm $D$, where $\text{End}(E) = \mathcal{O}$.</description></item><item><title>Subroutines when Computing Isogenies from Ideals</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-to-isogeny-subroutines/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 15:18:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/ideal-to-isogeny-subroutines/</guid><description>At a high level, the purpose of the algorithm IdealToIsogenyFromKLPT() is to compute the isogeny corresponding to a given ideal (via the Deuring Correspondence). We discuss how it is implemented in more depth in Computing Isogenies From Ideals.
In this blogpost, however, we discuss the two main subroutines in IdealToIsogenyFromKLPT():
IdealToIsogenyCoprime() to translate and evaluate $T$-isogenies (where $T$ is coprime to $\ell$) IdealToIsogenySmallFromKLPT() to translate $\ell^f$-isogenies using the output of IdealToIsogenyCoprime().</description></item><item><title>Meet in the Middle Isogenies</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/meet-in-the-middle/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 14:10:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/meet-in-the-middle/</guid><description>During IdealToIsogenySmallFromKLPT(), two isogenies $\psi_1 : E_3 \to E_5$, and $\psi_2 : E_\psi \to E_6$ are computed. The codomains of these isogenies are separated by an unknown degree $\ell^\Delta$ isogeny $\eta: E_5 \to E_6$. To compute the output of the function IdealToIsogenySmallFromKLPT(), the isogeny $\eta$ must first be recovered through brute force.
The SQISign paper recommends implementing this as a meet in the middle algorithm which will have complexity $O(\sqrt{\ell^{\Delta}})$. This page details our implementation of this algorithm.</description></item><item><title>Small Steps from Curves with Small Endomorphisms</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/small-steps/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 14:10:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/small-steps/</guid><description>This page is used to explain the optional argument end_close_to_E0 available to IdealToIsogenyFromKLPT() and why it is necessary to include such that the algorithm can run successfully in SQISign for both keygen() and response(). For a more detailed description of the algorithm IdealToIsogenyFromKLPT(), read the page Computing Isogenies from Ideals.
Motivation We first compute the ideal filtration
$$ I = \tilde{I}_v \subset \dots \subset \tilde{I}_1 \subset \tilde{I}_0, $$
where each quotient $I_m = \tilde{I}_{m}/\tilde{I}_{m-1}$ has norm $\ell^{\text{step}}$.</description></item><item><title>Modifying Compression</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/compression/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 18:14:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/compression/</guid><description>Upon receiving the response $\sigma$, the verifier needs to ensure that it is an isogeny $E_A \rightarrow E_2$ of degree $D$, such that the composition with the challenge isogeny is cyclic. To send the response to the verifier, we want to find a compact and efficient representation of $\sigma$ that can be sent to the verifier.
We found that we needed to include an additional bit into the compressed representation $S$ of the response isogeny $\sigma: E_A \to E_2$ to ensure that it is correctly extracted during decompression.</description></item><item><title>Future Work</title><link>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/future-work/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 22:07:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learningtosqi.github.io/posts/future-work/</guid><description>New SQISign Currently, our implementation follows the original 2020 paper: SQISign: compact post-quantum signatures from quaternions and isogenies, by Luca De Feo, David Kohel, Antonin Leroux, Christophe Petit, and Benjamin Wesolowski.
However, in 2022, an eprint was put online called New algorithms for the Deuring correspondence, which has new descriptions of ideal to kernel algorithms which estimate an approximate two-fold speed up for both keygen and signing.
At the time of writing this blog, the paper has just been updated ready for EUROCRYPT 2023: New algorithms for the Deuring correspondence: toward practical and secure SQISign signatures, by Luca De Feo, Antonin Leroux, Patrick Longa and Benjamin Wesolowski.</description></item></channel></rss>